<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examen of the way of teaching the Latin tongue to little children, by use alone Englished out of French.</title>
            <title>Examen de la manier d'enseigner de latin aux enfans. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12004330</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12004330</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52253</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38968)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52253)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 815:3 or 914:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examen of the way of teaching the Latin tongue to little children, by use alone Englished out of French.</title>
                  <title>Examen de la manier d'enseigner de latin aux enfans. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.N. for J. Martyn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Original published as Examen de la manier d'enseigner de latin aux enfans.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 88.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reels 815:3 and 914:23.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin language --  Study and teaching.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52253:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52253:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXAMEN Of the WAY OF <hi>Teaching the Latin Tongue</hi> TO <hi>Little Children,</hi> BY Uſe alone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed out of</hi> FRENCH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>J. Martyn</hi> Printer to the <hi>R. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> without <hi>Temp'e-Bar,</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52253:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52253:2"/>
            <head>AN EXAMEN Of the Way of Teaching the <hi>Latine Tongue</hi> to Little Children, by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe alone.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Occaſion of this Writing.</head>
               <p>'<seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>is ſome Months ſince, that there was much diſcourſe at <hi>Paris</hi> about a young Child, knowing no other Language, but <hi>Latin,</hi> and uſing the ſame as other Infants do their Mother-tong. A perſon of quality
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52253:3"/>having made mention of it to the King, his <hi>Majeſty</hi> would ſee it; and thereupon it was ſeen by all the Court. Every body diſcourſed of the confidence of the Child, of the pretty things it ſpake and of its man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeaking them. I have ſeen it twice, and entertain'd it well nigh three hours, and muſt confeſs, it ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed me, notwithſtanding all I had heard ſaid of it before, to its advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
               <p>This Child had not yet <hi>four</hi> years. I found it very chearful, active and confident; and withall obſerv'd judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and a good nature in all it did. I ſpoke to it of many things, which was impoſſible, it could fore-ſee. It underſtood very well all I ſaid to it, and anſwer'd me with ſuch frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that whatſoever I may ſpeake of it, I ſhall never make it appeare ſo much, as it is. I have not heard it ſpeak one word, which was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52253:3"/>and it hath ev'n the dexterity to vary the expreſſions, when it is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g'd to ſay often the ſame thing. Jt commits no fault in the <hi>Inflexions,</hi> and is not only exact in what it ſpeaks, but with a ſtrange quickneſs taketh up and corrects thoſe, that ſpeak not right. Some body having ask'd it, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ibis â prandio;</hi> it rectifi'd him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Quo <hi>ibis?</hi> An other ſaying, <hi>Conſcendere in equo,</hi> he reply'd' <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum conſcendere.</hi> Another uſing the word <hi>Agaſo,</hi> to ſignifie a <hi>Groom of the Stable,</hi> this Child at firſt percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not this impropriety; but one of them, that were preſent giving it to underſtand, that they were ſpeaking of a man that leads a horſe, he ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted the word <hi>Equiſo</hi> to him that had committed this fault. Which few Inſtances may ſhew, what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs it obſerves in <hi>Words.</hi> Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alſo might be given for a mark of its Iudgement in ſuch particulars,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52253:4"/>as occurred where it was, if we were not to Iudge of the Education of a Child, rather by the connexion and ſequele of all its words, than by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain particular occurrences; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt no Child, which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally will not ſay ſomething or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is ſurpriſing.</p>
               <p>Every body will eaſily gueſs, that this Child can never have had other Rules for its language, than <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Converſation.</hi> The Father thereof was happy in finding two friends honeſt and able, who asked it of him upon its being wean'd. 'Tis manifeſt, that they have omitted nothing that might ſerve either for giving it the purity of the Language, or for poſſeſſing it with good Manners; and that their cheif care and induſtry, to render the Child what it is, conſiſted, as for <hi>Manners,</hi> in ſpeaking all things to it with diſcretion, in removing it from all evill Examples, and in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52253:4"/>to it nothing but what was harmleſs and honeſt; and what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd the <hi>Language,</hi> in uſing none but proper and fit words, and in reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in its preſence thoſe, that ſpoke falſe. This is the reflexion, which a very Wiſe and very Vertuous Princeſſe made upon this Child, after ſhe had ſeen it above an hour converſe with a Perſon of quality; adding, That, how advantagious ſoever the way of teaching a Language (which is left no where but in Books) might ſeem to her, yet ſhe was farr more ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed at the Openneſs of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this Child, than its Ability in ſpeaking this Language; although ſhe believed, that the way, wherin it had been taught, had much contributed to make it ſo rational and ſo well diſpoſed, as it was.</p>
               <p>Now the ſucceſs of this Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Importance of Learning Arts and Sciences, wherewith the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52253:5"/>Latin Tong is ſo much link'd, and the extreme difficulty there is in the Common ways of learning it, have miniſtred unto me ſome thoughts and conſiderations, which I judged were not amiſs to be put in writing; although I think not, I ſhall perſuade all, that ſhall take the pains of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them; and although I alſo know, that many of thoſe, who ſhall have the ſame thoughts with me, ſhall not be in a condition to put them in execution and practiſe, for want ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a ſubject, or of perſons ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to make ſuch an attempt ſuccesfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52253:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That this way of Teaching languages is very Antient, and infallible.</head>
               <p>IN the mean time, there is nothing more Natural, nor more Infallible, than this ſucceſs; and I wonder leſs, that the Maſters of this Child reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to inſtruct it after this manner, than that all the world does not the like. For <hi>firſt,</hi> no man is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that ſince the beginning of the World unto this day every one hath learnt his Mother-tong <hi>without Rules,</hi> and ſpoken it better, than any other. <hi>Secondly,</hi> as to forrain Languages, all know likewiſe, that the ſhorteſt, ſureſt and eaſieſt means of learning them, is, to goe into the Contry's, where they are Vulgar, where Rules
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52253:6"/>are needleſs to learn them. <hi>Thidly,</hi> 'tis alſo knowne, that <hi>Montagne</hi> learnt the <hi>Latin</hi> tongue from the Breaſt; which way of learning it ſucceeded ſo well, that this Example alone was ſufficient to encourage the attempt of thoſe, whom we now ſpeak of.</p>
               <p>There is therefore no reaſon at all to wonder either at the undertaking, or the ſucceſs. Mean while 'tis Iuſt, to give them, in both, the honour due unto them. <hi>Firſt,</hi> though the Way propoſ'd be <hi>Infallible,</hi> yet 'tis certain, that there are not many perſons fit to accompliſh ſo readily and ſo fully, what they have done. And I cannot ſay, that the meeting with a child of good natural parts hath much helped them. For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that Children, whether they be ſprightly or no, learn almoſt equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well their Mother-tong, it appears not, that this Child, we ſpeak of, had any advantage of that nature
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52253:6"/>above many others. Me thinks, I obſerve nothing more in him, than a habit of reaſoning, and a certain docibleneſs, which ſeems to proceed from nothing elſe, than from the manner, which thoſe that have taught him, lived and converſed with him in. And I am confirm'd in this thought by the Example of two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Children very young, that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the ſame conduct, and that have almoſt nothing Childiſh in them, but the Motions and gayneſs, which are inſeparable from that age, and which are ſo neceſſary for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> the Example of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagne</hi> did not much remove the doubts, which might rationally occur in this matter. We know nothing of it, but what himſelf ſaith of it; and it might be doubted, Whether the Eſſay, that was made of this method upon his perſon had all the ſucceſs, he relateth; this Author
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52253:7"/>having with the qualities, that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him eſteem'd, the ill repute of ſetting too high a prize on thoſe things, that were advantagious to him, or which he believed to be ſuch. It might alſo be doubted, Whether the thing would ſucceed in ſo popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a city, as <hi>Paris,</hi> and with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not lodging alone, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing maſters of thoſe, they lodge with; it having ſucceeded in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes of <hi>Perigort,</hi> and in a Caſtle, where all obeyed <hi>Montagne</hi>'s Father, who had impoſed ſilence to all that were about his ſon, thoſe excepted, that could ſpeak <hi>Latin</hi> to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> it might be fear'd, that either the thing would not ſucceed, or it would be requiſite to maintain a number of good <hi>Latiniſts</hi> about this Child, as the Father of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagne</hi> had done about his Son, which would have cauſed great expenſes.</p>
               <p>It is eaſie, to ſatisfy all theſe doubts
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52253:7"/>after the Event; but it was not ſo eaſie to foreſee it, and yet leſs eaſie, well to manage ſuch a deſigne. When one ſees things done, they are not found difficult, and often they are found the more eaſy and the more natural, the more pains they have coſt to do them. Nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears more eaſy to invent, than <hi>Printing</hi> and the <hi>Sea-compaſs,</hi> and nothing more obvious, than to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the <hi>Circulation of the Blood.</hi> The Principles of it have been known more than 1800 years agoe. There wanted nothing, but to make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions. And yet the World hath been, as 'twere, aſleep untill theſe later times, in things of that impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which now appear ſo clear and eaſy, that it ſeems not credible, either that they ſhould not have been underſtood, or that there ſhould have interpoſed the leaſt difficulty in putting them in execution. But we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52253:8"/>doe not therefore eſteem thoſe the leſs, that have ſhew'd them us; for, either we muſt univerſally diſeſteem all men, that have been before us, for not having found thoſe things, which preſented themſelves to them as 'twere of their own accord; or we are highly to eſteem thoſe, who had the Wit and Iudgement to ſee thoſe conſequences, which ſo many men had not perceived for ſo many Ages.</p>
               <p>I think, I doe not uſe too much exaggeration, when I compare this manner of teaching Infants <hi>Latin</hi> with the Invention of <hi>Printing</hi> and the <hi>Sea-Compaſs,</hi> and to the Diſcovery of the <hi>Bloods Circulation;</hi> and poſſibly thoſe, that ſhall read this, will Iudge of it as I doe, when they ſhall have conſidered; <hi>firſt,</hi> How important it is to know the <hi>Latin</hi> tongue. <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The advantages, that occurre in this manner of teaching it, to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52253:8"/>know it well. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of thoſe advantages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The importance of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tong.</head>
               <p>'TIs needleſs, to inſiſt much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſhewing the Importance of the <hi>Latin Tongue.</hi> 'Tis known to all, that there is no publick Profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of any ſcience to be made (the <hi>Mathematicks</hi> perhaps excepted) without knowing that Tong. Not that it is abſolutely neceſſary for the Learning of any of the humane ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but that 'tis an eſtabliſh't Cuſtom, to examine and to exerciſe in <hi>Latin,</hi> as well thoſe that are to be admitted to the practiſe of the Law and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, as thoſe, that are to be received into Eccleſiaſticall Functions. 'Tis alſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52253:9"/>obvious, how uſefull it is to know that Tongue, not onely to be able to read prophane Authors in their own language, but alſo to underſtand the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar Latin Tranſlation</hi> of the Bible, and the <hi>Latin Fathers:</hi> That 'tis alſo little leſs than abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, not only to underſtand it, but alſo to write and ſpeak it, if you will have any correſpondence with the more Northern Nations, either in affairs of State, or in matter of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Sciences: That it renders very eaſy to us the underſtanding of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Jtalian:</hi> Laſtly, That a man can ſcarce paſs for an Able man, except he underſtand <hi>Latin,</hi> Cuſtome here carrying it from Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; though one may know it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being an Able man, and become very knowing and very able without underſtanding it.</p>
               <p>Although the greateſt part of the World think not on all theſe reaſons,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52253:9"/>'tis obvious that moſt are perſwaded (I know not <hi>How</hi>) of the neceſſity of knowing the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as their Children are ſubjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to incredible pains to learn it, and ſince alſo one of the moſt coſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parts of our life is ſacrific'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. In the mean time this is clear, That what uſe ſoever may be made of the knowledg of this Tongue, yet that were to be eſteem'd very inconſiderable, if it ſhould take us off from the knowledge of <hi>Things.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> An Examen of the Common way of Teaching Latin.</head>
               <p>IT is therefore ſtrange enough, that commonly for the Teaching of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> (which may be called the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> of the <hi>Learn'd</hi>) there is uſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52253:10"/>ſuch a way, of which the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable effect is, to put moſt men <hi>out</hi> of the way to become Learn'd, and to bring it to paſs, That they know a few things very late and very imperfectly. And theſe inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are the more intolerable, that that Conduct, after it hath needleſly engag'd us to preferre the knowledg of <hi>Words'</hi> to that of <hi>Things</hi> (which is a great Evill) doth not conduce to teach us even that Language, which we have ſacrificed all unto. Above all things, it being moſt eaſie, to re-eſtabliſh an Antient tryed way, which is infallible eaſie, ſhort, and as commodious for the knowledg of <hi>Things,</hi> as advantagious for the knowledge of <hi>Words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet this is very near, what happens in the Ordinary method of Teaching Latin to Children. All which will appear by what follows. But I believe, that all thoſe, who
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52253:10"/>ſhall read this Tract, doe acknowledge before-hand, that one cannot ſhew the advantages of <hi>our</hi> way of Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generally all Tongues, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the <hi>Latin,</hi> by <hi>Vſe,</hi> but by oppoſing it to the defectiveneſs of the Rules, that conſtitute the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> Method; And I hope, they will in the ſequele eaſily diſtinguiſh thoſe defects that <hi>cannot</hi> be avoided, from ſuch, as <hi>may,</hi> without changing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together the common road; and that they will ſoon find, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever care be taken to better it, it will never ſo be advantagious as this, which we recommend; as alſo that it would not be impoſſible to render this as Univerſall and as Publick, as that, which hath been hitherto recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and practis'd, at leaſt for the Rich and Great, and perhaps for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alſo of a mean Condition.</p>
               <p>They commonly put their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into the Colledg at the age
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52253:11"/>of 6. or 7. years, and keep them there till 17. or 18. One forgets eaſily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough pains that are paſſed, but thoſe that have been endured all that time, are ſo long and ſo irkſome, that with very little thinking they may eaſily be remembred. I ſpeak not of Children untowardly born; I ſpeak of thoſe, that have a mind to learn, and are naturally diſpoſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: What trouble and vexation muſt they undergoe, to diſtinguiſh all the parts of a diſcourſe; to learn all the inflections or Accidents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; to connect them for good ſence; to know all their reſpects and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences; to learn words; to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh all their ſignifications and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties; to apprehend the order they are to keep to one another <hi>&amp;c?</hi> All theſe things are certainly very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult in themſelves, and are the more ſo to Children, in that they leſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what it means, that they are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52253:11"/>taken all at once from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of the World to ſpeake a language to them, they underſtand not, which they think they need not, and which affords them no pleaſure at all, but rather deprives them of al their divertiſements, gives them much trouble, and draws on them all the little puniſhments, and tedious treatments which they cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from, how much ſoever you be inclined to educate them with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity and gentleneſs. When a Child is puniſht for having beaten another, for lying, ſtealing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands well enough, that it hath done ill; and though it ſhould not know it, yet it ſeeth that in thoſe things there is equal Iuſtice done to all chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, they paſſing every where for faults which deſerve puniſhment: But it would be pretty difficult, to give to a little child a reaſon, naturall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, of the evill it hath done, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52253:12"/>of the puniſhment it hath deſerved for having miſ-conſtrued an <hi>Adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> with a <hi>Subſtantive,</hi> and why we exact that of him, which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not from ſo many other Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who doe no more than to read, write and ſpeak their Language, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being oblig'd to take notice ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Declenſions,</hi> or <hi>Conjugations,</hi> or <hi>Syntax,</hi> or <hi>Heteroclites,</hi> nor any of all thoſe perplexities of <hi>Tenſes, Caſes, Perſons, Articles,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</hi> 'Tis notorious, how great an averſion we naturally have from all what is conſtrain'd, and how ſure a means it is to hinder Children from doing a thing, to command them to doe it, though even that, which they are commanded, ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to them. And thence 'tis eaſie to gueſs, what averſion they naturally conceive for a thing painfull in it ſelf, wherein it ſeems, that we command them only to command
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52253:12"/>them. And the whole ſequele of their Studies may appear, as if we would make them believe, we took a kind of pleaſure in tormenting them, or at leaſt that we indulged them not enough, ſince, beſides the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which ſeem unavoidable, we alſo engage them in ſuch, as might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided; as ſome Perſons very able and very well verſed in the Art of Teaching Children have ſhew'd, both by their <hi>Writings,</hi> and by the <hi>Tayals</hi> they have made.</p>
               <p>In thoſe <hi>Writings</hi> it hath been made appear, <hi>firſt,</hi> Of what importance it would be, to give (for example) in French the Rules of the Latin Tongue, that are given in Latin. <hi>Secondly,</hi> How much more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious it would be, to make Children read Authors as ſoon as they have learnt the more general Rules of the <hi>Grammar,</hi> and not to oblige them to tranſlate <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Latin,</hi> but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52253:13"/>when they ſhall have known, by the reading of Authors, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of the words, their order and dependences. We ſhall not repeat here, what may be ſeen in thoſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; but t'is eaſie to infer from what is there layd down (which expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience confirms every day) that 'tis almoſt impoſſible, that a young man, educated after that manner, entring into <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> can therein produce any thing but what is very mediocre, ſince 'tis impoſſible to write well in a Language, which one underſtands not well, and well to underſtand a <hi>dead</hi> Tongue, but by a long uſe of Authors; and that the Schollars, who are taught it, have almoſt read nothing of Authors in the other <hi>Forms.</hi> Thus they commonly ſpend two yeares in that <hi>Form</hi> in compoſing a Language they underſtand nor. 'Tis true, that then 'tis endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r'd to make them underſtand it by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52253:13"/>Reading; but 'tis too late, to make them begin what they ſhould have done before they undertook any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Thus all, they can have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited at the end of thoſe two yeares, is, to have got by their Reading ſome reliſh for the Latin Tongue, yet without any readineſs either to expreſs themſelves therein in familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, or to write of any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable matter in the ſame; which two things are of a more important, more frequent and more univerſal Uſe, than thoſe <hi>Themes</hi> in the Air, which are given them to dilate upon, teaching them to ſay that in many pages, which they might ſay in few lines.</p>
               <p>It is needleſs to add here the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, there is in all this as to <hi>Rhetorick;</hi> tis ſufficient to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that none but a very inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable progreſs can be made in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Tongue the Old way. And yet that is all the fruit of <hi>C.</hi> or. 7. yeares:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52253:14"/>In regard of which ſlender proficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, it would be the more proper not to expoſe a young habit, which hath coſt ſo much, and is yet ſo feeble, to ſo many things, that may weaken it. But yet this is that, which is done: to which two faults may be ioyned a <hi>third,</hi> perhaps the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable; <hi>viz.</hi> That Children are made to paſs from <hi>Rhetorick</hi> to <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy.</hi> There they remain two yeares; during which time they are ſpoken to and are made to ſpeak in a Language, that is neither French nor Latin. There is almoſt no Latin in it, but the Terminations of words: certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you can find nothing of <hi>true</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinity there. I ſee nothing more capable to make them forget Latin, than this Philoſophical Latin; and I am perſwaded, that it maketh them loſe more the true guſt of it, than the Tongue, of all others moſt remote from Latin. And yet it would be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52253:14"/>very eaſy to teach them the ſame things in the true purity of that Tongue. There is nothing more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate nor more acute in all <hi>Logick,</hi> than in the <hi>Academick</hi> Queſtions of <hi>Cicero;</hi> there is nothing greater nor ſublimer in the <hi>Morals,</hi> than in the Entertainments of <hi>Tuſculum,</hi> in the Books of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Ill,</hi> and in thoſe of the <hi>Duties</hi> of the <hi>Civil Life:</hi> There is nothing more exact in <hi>Natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,</hi> than in the Books of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Gods,</hi> and the Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Traduction of <hi>Timeus</hi> by the ſame Author. In a word, I am perſwaded, that if one had a mind to copy with attention thoſe Originals, one might find matter and forme to frame thence a very dogmatical, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry clear, and very Latine Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</p>
               <p>It is now eaſie to conclude from all that hath been ſaid, that one learns in the common Schooles very
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52253:15"/>
                  <hi>litle</hi> Latin with <hi>great</hi> pain and with great expence of time: To which may be added, That children forget the beſt part of what they knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they entred them, which is, their own Mother-tongue and the Writing thereof, and that they faile to learn what they might have learnt all that time, they have beſtow'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a little Latin.</p>
               <p>If now we ſhall put it into the ballance, on one ſide, the little that is gain'd, the much that is loſt, and that might alſo have been acquired; and on the other ſide, the Uſes, that one may propoſe to one's ſelf in the Learning of that Language, I doe not doubt but it will appear too coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at that rate, and that all will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, it were better for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt number of thoſe, who learn it, not to know it at all, than to know it, ever perfectly, at that price and on thoſe conditions, which have been diſcourſed of.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:52253:15"/>
               <p>'Tis true, that one might learn it by <hi>Rules</hi> with more eaſe, in leſs time, and more perfectly; <hi>firſt,</hi> by giveing the Rules (e. g.) in <hi>French,</hi> and in a ſmaller number: <hi>ſecondly,</hi> by making the Learners to tranſlate out of Latin into French, and not out of French into Latin, but after a long uſe of Latin Authors: <hi>thirdly,</hi> in delivering unto them in <hi>true</hi> Latin whatever appertains to Philoſophy. But I doe not think, that by thoſe things you ſhall ever equall the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor the eaſineſs, nor the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which proceed from Uſe and Converſe alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52253:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> An Examen of the Way here propoſed.</head>
               <p>TO be perſwaded of the fitneſs thereof, we need no more but conſider the Conduct, that hath been uſed in the Teaching of this Infant, as I have collected it from the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Conferences, had by me with its Maſters, and as it is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved hereafter.</p>
               <p>The Child was but twenty and two Months of Age, when they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook it, upon its being wean'd from the breaſt. They need not be taken in hand younger. It is advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable to ſtay, till their health be ſomewhat confirm'd in the Change of Dyet; you may therefore ſtay till they have 25. or 26 Months. 'Tis
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52253:16"/>not material, if they have learnt of their Nurſes ſome words of their Mother-tongue; that will be ſoon forgot, as Experience ſhows.</p>
               <p>Thoſe, that have bred up this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, were very ready to undertake afterwards two others, the one of which had 31. Months, and ſpake many words of our Language; but they both forgot all they knew of it, within 2. or 3. weeks. I have ſeen the firſt, who in a Months time had learnt ſo much Latin, as he had known <hi>French;</hi> and I ſaw alſo the other, who in 5. weeks had learnt to ſpeak much more Latin, than before he could ſay words in his Mother-tongue. There is always with them one of their Maſters, and the biggeſt of the three Children ſerves in a manner for a third Maſter to the other two. The Servants, that take care of them, know ſo much Latin, as needs to ſpeak to them, and to correct them,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52253:17"/>when they ſpeak amiſs in familiar matters. The firſt of them hath been thus brought up till he was 4. years of age; and his Maſters now begin to put him to learn <hi>French;</hi> therein following the Conduct of <hi>Quintilian,</hi> who was not for being ſuperſtitiouſly tyed from teaching Children for a long time no other Tongue but the <hi>Greek,</hi> but adviſ'd, that the learning of the <hi>Latin</hi> ſhould ſoon follow after, and ſo both Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages be cultivated together.</p>
               <p>This cannot want good ſucceſs. Nor is it to be fear'd, that the two Languages will be confounded, ſince, beſides the Example of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who obſerv'd that practiſe, we have alſo that of ſome modern Nations, that are not reputed to have more wit, than We; among whom Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren learn at the ſame time, at leaſt two Languages very different: As the Children of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52253:17"/>learn the vulgar <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Turkiſh;</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Suiſſes</hi> of <hi>Newcaſtel</hi> and almoſt all <hi>Flemmings,</hi> who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> learn very often the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> too.</p>
               <p>This Conſideration may put us upon the thoughts to teach <hi>Latin</hi> after this way not only ſuch Children as know not yet any Language, but alſo thoſe, that doe already ſpeak their Mother-tong, <hi>viz.</hi> by putting them among thoſe, who ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Latin;</hi> if there were not ſome danger of confounding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarding thoſe, who are yet weak in <hi>this</hi> Language. But this Confuſion may be prevented; <hi>firſt,</hi> by forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe Children, that are already capable of reaſon, to ſpeak their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-tong in the preſent of the other leſſer children allowing certain houres for entertaining them in their Mother-tong. <hi>Secondly,</hi> by taking of thoſe Children, able to ſpeak their Mother-tongue,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52253:18"/>but one at a time, that ſo the inability, which ſhall be in all the reſt, of anſwering him, when he ſhall ſpeak to them in his Language, may oblige him to ſtrive to ſpeak to them in theirs; with the reſerve of giveing him a Companion, when he ſhall have gain'd an equal habit in both Tongues. And as thoſe, that know nothing but their Mother-tongue, ſhall have been taught by the Converſation of thoſe, who ſpeak nothing but <hi>Latin;</hi> ſo might alſo ſuch, as know nothing but <hi>Latin,</hi> be inſtructed by the Converſation of thoſe, that know their Mother-tong; diſtinguiſhing the hours, when it ſhould be permitted to ſpeak the Mother-tongue, from thoſe, when it ſhould be allow'd to ſpeak <hi>Latin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this might be carried ſo farr, as to make even perſons advanced in Age capable to learn the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue: which might be done by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52253:18"/>putting together many Men able in <hi>that</hi> Language, who ſhould make, as 'twere, a little <hi>Latin</hi> Republick: Which would be very eaſie, if the <hi>King,</hi> who hath done ſo many great and difficult things, would think fit to iſſue his Orders for it, which perhaps would be none of the leaſt Objects, that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to himſelf; as may appear by the ſequele of this Writing.</p>
               <p>This is the whole Myſtery of this Inſtruction, in what regards the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tong: Upon which may be made the following reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52253:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Reflections upon this Way; and firſt that it is <hi>eaſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is nothing in the world more Eaſie for Children, than to learn <hi>Latin</hi> this way. It is ſo natural, to deſire to underſtand what others ſay, and to make them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand our thoughts, that 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, but Children will have a ſtrong bent of themſelves to learn that Language, which is ſpoken in their preſence. As this Tongue mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelf in all their divertiſements, in all their wants, they ſtrive of their own accord to learn the ſame. They doe not ſo much as <hi>think</hi> to learn it, and even that maketh them learn it the better. The little boy, who hath miniſtred the occaſion to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52253:19"/>this Writiug, could not, two monthes a goe, ſay the <hi>Pater noſter</hi> without failing and heſitating, how great care ſoever had been taken to repeate it to him for two years. Mean time he hath learnt a great number of Words and Inflections, of which he hath made himſelf maſter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any body's taking any other care, but of ſpeaking to and anſwering him. He hath never been threatn'd nor puniſh'd to learn this Language: which is of no ſmal importance. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, menaces, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are not only preſent evils, which <hi>Humanity</hi> requireth ſhould be ſpar'd as much as is poſſible; but they are alſo Sources of evils, which <hi>Prudence</hi> oblieges to prevent. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtreitens the Heart like <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Grief;</hi> and I know not, to which of theſe two, the Soule or the Body, thoſe two paſſions are moſt contrary. The tediouſneſs of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52253:20"/>learning a leſſon one loves not, the fear of being puniſh't if one ſay it ill, the fretfulneſs for haveing been puniſh't, keep Children always al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd, and make them looſe a great part of that Ingenuity, Cheerfulneſs and Frankneſs, they have, in an Age, wherein nothing more ſhould be thought on, than to confirm their health, by forming them at the ſame time to an innocent gayneſs, to a confidence in thoſe, who have the conduct of them, to a freedome from choller, to a love of their duty, and to a couſideration, from the conduct uſed towards them, that <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in all things are the only good, which Men put a value upon.</p>
               <p>The beſt means to ſink into the Minds of Children this <hi>Maxime</hi> (which is more important to Society, than all the Languages of the world) is to accuſtome them not to be puniſht, as near as may be, but for actions
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52253:20"/>repugnant to Iuſtice. And that will not only ſerve to cauſe them to make a great diſtinction of thoſe kinds of duties, but alſo to bind them the more to the obſervance of them, in that the puniſhments becoming more rare, they accuſtom themſelves leſs to, and are the more ſenſible of them. This is not ſaid, as if we were not oblig'd, ſometimes to chaſtiſe them for other faults; but it is as well the ſurer, as the better, not to put our ſelves upon a neceſſity of multiplying thoſe kinds of chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and no man can doubt that they are cut off, when the Rules of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue are ſo.</p>
               <p>You may make Children under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand reaſon in other, even painfull, things, as the learning to <hi>Read,</hi> and to <hi>Write &amp;c.</hi> and you may cauſe them even to be deſirous of it. Now if this be of conſequence for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of a middle condition, 'tis the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52253:21"/>more ſo for thoſe of <hi>Grandees,</hi> in whom the difficulty of learning thoſe things is an almoſt invincible obſtacle to learn them, although the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg thereof is little leſs neceſſary to them.</p>
               <p>It is therefore very eaſie to teach them the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue after this manner, and there is a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in this eaſineſs. But it is not eaſie to know as much <hi>Latin</hi> as needs, to entertaine <hi>them</hi> with that latitude and freedom, which is requiſite. You muſt know to play, and to ſpeak ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in <hi>Latin;</hi> to entertaine them during the two firſt two years with whatever may be incident in the moſt familiar diſcourſes; which extends further then one is aware of. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to forme their Manners, and to try their vnderſtanding for employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in what 'tis capable of, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be for Reaſoning, or for Hiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory, or for Deſcriptions <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52253:21"/>to increaſe inſenſibly this little ſtock, to run through the moſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Arts, and to uſe in their preſence the general terms thereof; and to ſpeak all with that frankneſs and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, which is ſo peculiar to that Tongue, and to ſay nothing but what's exact both for the <hi>Words</hi> and the <hi>Matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is to be wiſh'd, that all theſe things may concurr for this <hi>Latin</hi> converſe with Children, and for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them ſpeak according to their capacity, and with all deſirable free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. This is difficult enough in general, becauſe 'tis not eaſy to find many, that well vnderſtand even their Mother-tongue to that extent and ſo particularly; and becauſe in the <hi>Latin</hi> there are difficulty's to be met with, that are not found in the vulgar Tongues. Habits, Utenſils. Manners, Politicks, Government, Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having been chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52253:22"/>and ſome Arts invented, ſince the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue hath ceaſ'd to be Vulgar, 'tis hard enough to know, how to expreſs all thoſe things in that Language. Yet 'tis certaine, that we find many things in Antiquity, which have a great affinitie with our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties, and that, when we find none ſuch, we muſt be allow'd to form words after the model and by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogy of what is antient. And this hath been very well obſerved by thoſe, that have inſtructed this Infant. But we doe not find our ſelves often in that neceſſity: For, the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue reacheth farther than we imagine; there is almoſt nothing, which is not found expreſs'd in Books; and to be convinced of that, we need but caſt our Eyes upon <hi>Terence, Plautus, Pliny, Columella, Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Iuſtinian.</hi> For there is almoſt nothing, whether great or ſmall, common or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, which may not be found in thoſe Authors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:52253:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAHP. VII.</hi> That this way is <hi>Short.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT cannot be otherwiſe, but that this manner of Teaching <hi>Latin</hi> muſt be <hi>Short,</hi> ſince it is ſo <hi>Eaſie.</hi> But it will not be amiſſe to conſider, <hi>How much</hi> 'tis ſhorter than the <hi>Ordinary</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and how important it is, not to employ <hi>much</hi> time in Learning <hi>Latin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This little Boy hath learnt all he knows within the ſpace of two yeares, <hi>viz.</hi> from two years old to four; and he would know more, if a Child of that age were capable to underſtand more <hi>Things.</hi> But 'tis moraly cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that excepting the particular Terms of Arts and Sciences, he may know all the reſt before he ſhall have attain'd the Age of <hi>Nine</hi> years: which will be but <hi>Six</hi> yeares in all. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time one may teach this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52253:23"/>Child, and any other, as many <hi>Things,</hi> as he ſhall be able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend in ſo ſmall a time; ſo as the Language, which he learns, ſhall take up no time, nor retard at all the other knowledge, you ſhall inſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. To which if you add, that all that, which one could have done during all that time, would have been to teach him the ſame things, (e. g.) in <hi>French;</hi> it will follow, that the knowledge of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue will coſt him no more, but ſo much time preciſely, as he ſhall employ to learn ſo much French, as one knows of it at the going out of the Colledge. But now, I think not, it can be denied, that a Child, altogether left at the Age of nine years to his Mother-tongue, may not learne in two years at leaſt as much <hi>French,</hi> as one knows of it at the going out of the <hi>Claſſes</hi> or <hi>Forms</hi> at the Age of 15. or 16. yeares. Thus the <hi>Latin</hi> will coſt him
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52253:23"/>but two years; and it may be, it will coſt him much leſs. For, having been to ſee this little Boy ſince the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this, I have found, that he knows already a great many <hi>French</hi> words, which he takes delight to ſpeak; and that he will find a great facility in learning the reſt, when it ſhall be deſired. This being ſo, it may be affirm'd, that the <hi>Latin</hi> will almoſt take up none of his time, ſince he will not learne the leſs <hi>French;</hi> and that he will increaſe the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue in the ſame time, that ſhall be given him to learne <hi>French,</hi> and alſo that he will not the leſs know all ſorts of other things.</p>
               <p>'Tis certaine therefore, that this Way of Learning <hi>Latin</hi> is farr ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any other: which advantage is by ſo much the more conſiderable in this preſent Age, becauſe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hiſtories increaſe every day, but
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52253:24"/>there are alſo invented many new Arts and Practiſes; it being obſerv'd, that there hath been added more to the Arts and Inventions of the Antients within theſe laſt hundred years, than hath been done for Fourteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares before. But, foraſmuch as the Life of Men is not longer now, than it hath been before, it will be more neceſſary than ever, to redeem from that time, which hath been ſpent in the Learning of Languages, a portion to learn what is more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; eſpecially if that ſaving of time hinder us not from knowing as well the Tongues by this ſhort way, as by that, which hath been follow'd hitherto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52253:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> What it is, to know a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; and what this Way can contribute to the knowledg of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue.</head>
               <p>NOw ſince tis infallible, that the Latin Tongue is better to be learned by Vſe alone, than by all the Rules whatſoever, we ſhall, the better to underſtand this, explain, what is meant by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> and by <hi>well knowing a Language.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I mean by <hi>well knowing a Language</hi> (to begin with that) to ſpeak it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly and readily, and with that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as to ſpeak of all that falls un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der common diſcourſe, that is, of publick and private affairs, of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52253:25"/>vulgar Arts, and of what is common in them all. The <hi>Exactneſs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends not only the <hi>Inflexions</hi> and <hi>Conſtructions,</hi> ſo as to commit no fault there, but alſo the <hi>Propriety</hi> of the <hi>Words.</hi> And it ſuppoſes on one part, along cuſtome for the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections and conſtructions; and on the other, a great Choice of the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt words; which choice ſuppoſes a Copiouſneſs: And from both theſe, <hi>viz. Habit,</hi> and <hi>Copiouſneſs</hi> ariſeth <hi>Facility</hi> and <hi>Readineſs.</hi> And this I call the <hi>knowing</hi> of a Language.</p>
               <p>By <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I underſtand the Habit one acquireth both by the Reading of Authors, und a diſcourſe in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
               <p>Now we are to examine, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be true, that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> alone, thus underſtood, is able to contribute ſo much as is affirm'd, to make one ſpeak a Language with that exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, fulneſs, and facility.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52253:25"/>
               <p>The Plenty of words, and the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit a man hath to turn and to place them, doe ſerve much to ſpeak with exactneſs. Without this copiouſneſs and this habit, a man muſt often he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate, ſtop, and be ſilent: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in ſuch Accidents there is no failour as to exactneſs, foraſmuch as a man is ſilent, that he may not ſpeak ill; Yet, as we cannot ſay, that a man ſpeaks, when he is neceſſitated to be ſilent, ſo we cannot ſay, that ſuch an one ſpeaks <hi>exactly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as to the <hi>Extent,</hi> it cannot be denied, that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> renders it more large, when it begins with Infancy, than when it begins later. For, as we cannot educate a Child unto the age of 8. years, without telling it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, without entring with the ſame into many Colloquies, without reaſoning upon many accidents; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without deſcribing to it an infinity of things, that occur in daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52253:26"/>'tis certaine, that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but the Child muſt be initiated in all thoſe things, and imitate them upon occaſion; in a word, it muſt hear and ſpeak of many things, which are not ſpoken of in Schools; yet ſo as not to faile to hear alſo of thoſe matters, that may be there ſpoken of, as farr as they are of uſe. And this is, what reſpects <hi>perſonal Converſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as to <hi>Authors,</hi> 'tis likewiſe certaine, that the Child may be much more furniſht, our way, with what <hi>they</hi> can contribute to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a Language. The eldeſt of theſe Children, we ſpeak of, reads <hi>Phaedro,</hi> and underſtands of him all that is not above the reach of a Child; and it will underſtand very well at the age of <hi>ſix</hi> years, (at the lateſt,) what Children commonly underſtand not at the age of <hi>twelve.</hi> As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Child, taught by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> may employ in Reading all the time, that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52253:26"/>is ordinarily employ'd in the <hi>Grammar</hi> and in making of <hi>Themes,</hi> he may together with it at the ſame time have all theſe advantages, <hi>viz.</hi> To read Authors ſooner by <hi>four</hi> years, to underſtand them ſooner by <hi>ten,</hi> and continually to beſtow twice more time upon them, than others can doe; even then, when they begin to be moſt uſed to this Language, that is, from the age of twelve Years to that, when they come out of the Colledge. Thus he ſhall have read all the <hi>Latin</hi> Authors of all Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Arts within the time, that thoſe, who have been inſtructed after the common way, ſhall have been able but to read ſome few ſcraps of Orators, Hiſtorians and Poets.</p>
               <p>It cannot be, but that this mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of things read and underſtood, which ſerves ſo much to inſtill into the memory the termes of <hi>different</hi> art, to expreſs different things, (which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52253:27"/>is that, we call <hi>Extent</hi>) muſt alſo in-ſtill into the ſame, many different terms and ways to exrepſs the <hi>ſame</hi> thing; which is that, we call <hi>Copiousneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly 'tis impoſſible, but that the habit, we take from our Birth, and continue for 6. or 8. yeares, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine 8. or 9. yeares more, and which hath no other bounds during all that time, but of ſuch things as make up the converſe of civil men, muſt be incomparably larger and ſtronger, than that which we begin but to take at the age of 14. or 15. yeares, and which we continue but for 3. or 4. yeares, which alſo is much interrupted during that little time, and is bounded by a ſtile of Rhetorick, and by matters of a Philoſophical nature. Not that Children are not made to venture at ſpeaking <hi>Latin</hi> even in the loweſt Forms, and even in the playes they divert themſelves with in publick on their play-dayes; but we all know,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52253:27"/>that all that goes not beyond 20. or 30. phraſes, and that the neceſſity impos'd on them to ſpeak Latin, is ſo diſpleaſing to them, that it injures them more, (by accuſtoming them to ill manners, and by draining, as 'twere, their underſtanding by the cuſtome of not-thinking, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that of not ſpeaking,) than it can advantage them by remembring them of a few <hi>Latin</hi> words, which they have alwayes upon their lips, and beſides which they can ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but they commit abundance of groſs faults. Thus indeed they are not in a condition of ſpeaking La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, but when they are entred in <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick;</hi> and then they exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more in Writing than Speaking. This Exerciſe laſts not but two years, after which they enter into Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, where indeed they ſpeak more than they write, but all know, how they ſpeak there, and what
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52253:28"/>is to be hoped from thence.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Advantages of this Education above the received com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon one; <hi>viz.</hi> To learn <hi>more eaſily,</hi> in <hi>leſs time,</hi> and <hi>more perfectly.</hi> And theſe 3. advantages are not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in <hi>themſelves,</hi> but they are more ſo in their <hi>extent;</hi> ſince in the one way, we learn with the greateſt facility in the world, what in the other cannot be learnt but with the greateſt difficulties; and ſince the time, employ'd to learn our way, is valued almoſt nothing in the life of man, whereas that, which is ſpent in the other method, taketh up one of the conſiderableſt portions of our life; and laſtly ſince there is no compariſon between the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that may be acquir'd by <hi>Uſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and that little knowledge, which the <hi>Rules</hi> doe giue us.</p>
               <p>But how great ſoever the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages are, which we may propoſe to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52253:28"/>our ſelves in this Education by <hi>Uſe,</hi> there are ſome <hi>Inconveniences,</hi> which we muſt not conceale, and which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be examin'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The <hi>Inconveniences</hi> of this Way of Teaching Latin. I. That Mothers ſhall not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their own Children. What reſpect we are to have to this Inconvenience.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It may be reckon'd for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable Inconvenience, that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren know not their Mother-tongue for ſome years. Their Parents, that know no <hi>Latin,</hi> are all that while de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of the pleaſure of being diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the pretty Babes.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52253:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> This is nothing to thoſe, that have no Children, or that have many, or that love them but indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently. But I know that ſome perſons, otherwiſe very rational, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to have their Children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed this way, and having been ſatisfi'd as to ſome other difficulties, could not overcome this. In the mean time it appears not reaſonable to me. For, beſides that they ſhould conſider, that the Creator and Lord of all things does not give us our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for Puppets, to play and divert ourſelves with, without ſeeking and procuring their true good and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; they ought alſo to conſider, that the delight, which thoſe Children give us in ſo tender an age, can be but very ſlight and tranſitory; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the pleaſure of a good Education is rational, ſolid, and laſting as long as we live: Again, that the beſt teſtimony, they can give to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52253:29"/>and to others of a genuine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to their Children, is, the care they ſhall take to prevent their ill, and trouble; threatnings and pain, teares, vexation, and ſubjection; to all which another Education may ſubject them: Further, that a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Love obligeth them to preferr to an indiſcreet fondneſs the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, which their Children may reape from thence; and that, if they will have no regard to reaſon nor true and durable contentment, they ought at leaſt to conſider, that this ſilence of their Children to them will not laſt but from their ſecond to their fourth year of age, and that then they may begin to learne their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, and after they are confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m'd in the <hi>Latin,</hi> they may then keep them at home, and not looſe them out of their ſight. Theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ought, me thinks, to prevaile ſo as to render Mothers reaſonable in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52253:30"/>this point; and eſpecially the laſt. For it muſt be a very blind affection, not to be able to deprive on's ſelf of the contentment to ſee a Child, by committing it for a yeare or two to the truſt of ſome vertuous, civil, and rational perſon, after we have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble abandon'd them for two whole yeares to a Nurſe, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly hath neither moderation, nor civility, nor ſtore of tenderneſs in what concerns the rational care, due to children.</p>
               <p>But we may adde here, that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might be indulged in the fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to their Children, ſo farr as to let them ſee them ſometimes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any danger of hindring or ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their <hi>Latin.</hi> An hour of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption will not ſenſibly alter a cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome already taken; and I ſee, that Experience hath put thoſe, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducate ſuch Children, above this ſcruple, ſince they permit their Parents
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52253:30"/>to ſee them as often as they can reaſonably deſire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> That Children thus inſtructed ſhall know leſs their Mother-tongue. The miſtake in appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendnig ſuch an Inconvenince.</head>
               <p n="2">II. IT may be feared, that if Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould learn <hi>Latin</hi> firſt, they would leſs know the Tongue of their native Contry, than if they had learnt that firſt. This inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience would indeed be conſiderable, ſince 'tis important to know our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-tongue as perfectly, as is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But it is to be conſider'd; 1. That the <hi>Romans</hi> did not the leſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly learn <hi>Greek</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> although they had learnt their own Tongue a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52253:31"/>long time before they underſtood a word of <hi>Greek.</hi> 2. That the Childern, which are carried into forraign Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr'ys at the age of 9. or 10. years, there to learn the Language, doe not the leſs perfectly learn it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they have ſpoken their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-tongue for 8. or 9. yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. 3. That the Habit, which <hi>Montagne</hi> had acquired in the <hi>Latin</hi> tongue, did not hinder him from learning to ſpeak <hi>French</hi> as well as any man of his time, nor from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Pattern to one of the moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent men of his time, and who hath follow'd cloſeſt the Eloquence of the Antients.</p>
               <p>After theſe experiments, which are over-ſufficient to ſhew, that we ſhall not the leſs know our Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue for having learnt <hi>Latin</hi> firſt; it is needleſs to ſay, That the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> Tongue, being incomparably more difficult than our own, 'tis the more
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52253:31"/>fit to be learnt firſt of all. It will ſuffice to conſider, that <hi>Quintilian,</hi> exhbrting the <hi>Romans</hi> to learn <hi>Greek</hi> by Uſe alone and in their Infancy, ſticks not to alledg, That the <hi>Greek</hi> is much more difficult than the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin;</hi> which though he could have proved very eaſily and irrefragably, yet he loved rather, to doe it by this only reaſon; <hi>viz. That the</hi> Latin <hi>Tongue being at</hi> Rome <hi>more generally in uſe than the</hi> Greek, <hi>it would ſink into the memory, whether one would or no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt therefore not think, that this Preference, we give to the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> will hinder us in the knowledg of our Mother-tongue. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, 'tis eaſie to fore-ſee, that this is one of the greateſt advantages of this way of teaching, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes much to the knowledg of our Mother-tongue, by giving us leiſure to apply ourſelves more to it,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52253:32"/>than we could doe, if we learnt <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> by Rules. For, Children ſhall be able to read and ſpeak the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of their Country during the ſame time, which is commonly ſpent in learning the Rules, and during which we are, as 'twere forc'd, to forbid them the vſe of their Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue, that we may conſtraine them to apply themſelves only to <hi>Latin.</hi> to beat that into their heads.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:52253:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> III. That Children will haue nothing to doe from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth yeare of their Age to the fifteenth or ſixteenth. That this pretended inconvenience is a true Advantage for reall knowledg.</head>
               <p n="3">III. I Shonld be ſomewhat aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m'd to propoſe as an Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience the time ſav'd in this kind of Education, if this Inconvenience had not been very ſeriouſly propos'd by men otherwiſe of good ſenſe, and who even take a great care of the Education of their Children. They ſay then, that Children will have a very great Intervall of time from
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52253:33"/>Seaven to Fifteen or Sixteen years, that one ſhall not know, what to doe with them. The Anſwer to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to this Objection, is apparent enough from what hath been ſaid already; but it may not be amiſs, to propoſe it here at length.</p>
               <p>I doe not well know, how men, that complaine of the Shortneſs of the Life of man, and who are not able either to leſſen the number and vaſtneſs of things deſirable to be known, or to lengthen Life, ſhould want matter to employ it, as long as it ſhall laſt; and how thoſe, who avow, that <hi>Latin</hi> may be learnt till the age of ſeaven years, doubt, Whether there will be matter enough of more conſequence than the <hi>Latin</hi> Tong, to take up the time from ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years to fifteen. For, if you be onely in paine, how to employ them, without changing the ordinary courſe of inſtructing Children in Learning,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52253:33"/>you may give them to read from time to time, not only ſome of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Letters or Orations of <hi>Cicero,</hi> as is vſual, but alſo his Books of <hi>Oratory,</hi> and all his Philoſophical Works, wherein there is ſo much matter to learn and ſtudy; beſides, <hi>Quintilian, Terence,</hi> the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of <hi>Caeſar, Pliny</hi> the Younger, <hi>Livy, Saluſt, Columella, Tacitus, Pliny</hi> the Elder <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then <hi>Virgil,</hi> and ſome ſelected parts of <hi>Ovid, Horace, &amp;c.</hi> Further, the modern Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as <hi>Cambden, Strada, Maſſeus, Paulus Ievius, thuanus, &amp;c.</hi> not to mention ſo many <hi>French</hi> Books, that may be recommended to their peruſal during that time.</p>
               <p>It cannot be doubted, but that thoſe and ſuch like Books will em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy a Child untill it be 17. or 18. years old. 2. That ſuch employment will be more beneficiall to Children, than the rules of the Language. 3. That
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52253:34"/>it will be more pleaſing and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to them. 4. That it it will prove a great eaſe to the Parents, that cannot be at the charges requiſite to entertaine Tutors at home; foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as after their Children ſhall have learnt the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue by <hi>Uſe</hi> alone, they may be placed in <hi>Colledges,</hi> and there applyed to read Authors and Books written in the Language of their own Country, and eſpecially ſuch as belong to the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereof, during the time, which other Children ſpend in the inferior Schools; making them give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, of what they thus read, in the intervals of thoſe Schools.</p>
               <p>But as men are born to know o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, beſides Fables, Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick and Hiſtory, and ſince there is much knowledg more neceſſary, and Children are capable to be entred in ſuch knowledge; it will certainly be found, that that pretended <hi>Vacuum,</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:52253:34"/>how great ſoever it may appear, will hardly be ſufficient to learn, what a Child well born can and ought to know, before it is engaged in any Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>It would be the only means to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall the Antients by following their Example: For, they have not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed us, but in this, that they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in learning to Deſign, Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick, Geometry, Muſick, Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, Eloquence, Philoſophy, and Armes, that ſame time, we ſpend in learning the Rules of a Language. And this was that, which made their Philoſophers Souldiers, (as we may ſee in the perſon of <hi>Socrates</hi>) and their Generals Orators and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, as Xenophon, Alexander, Caeſar, and ſo many others.</p>
               <p>It would be proper, to ſhow in this place, that Children are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to underſtand ſome of the <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> and even the moſt important
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52253:35"/>and the moſt neceſſary. For that purpoſe it would ſuffice to alledge, that 'tis a thing that hath been try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not only by the Antients, as eaſily appeares by reading <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> where there are expreſs places, but alſo by the Moderns; and that moſt of the Sciences may be ſo propoſ'd, that the ſtudy of them will rather be a divertiſment, than a Labor. But it will be fit to add, that though we had no <hi>Experience</hi> of it, yet it were eaſy to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, that it would be ſo, by <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For thoſe, that are moſt tyed to the Teaching of <hi>Latin</hi> by Rules, muſt the more grant, that they ſuppoſe, Children are capable to underſtand them. But there is none of all thoſe, who teach <hi>Grammar,</hi> that knows not, that it contains, 1. The <hi>Ideas</hi> of the different parts of Diſcourſe. 2. The Rules for each of thoſe different parts. 3. The Rules of their Compoſition,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:52253:35"/>call'd <hi>Syntaxe.</hi> They muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Iudge Children capable to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all that, even from the Age of 6. or 7. years. And indeed, I have known ſome of that age, who had paſs'd thorough all thoſe 3. parts, and underſtood them. Now I ſay, that whoſoever is capable to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that knowledge by that way, is capable alſo to enter into almoſt all Scienecs; eſpecially thoſe, that Object of which is ſenſible.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What concerns the <hi>Ideas</hi> of the different parts of diſcours, we muſt grant, that they cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, unleſs you make, in <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> at leaſt, the diſtinction of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Accident, Place, Time, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Paſſion, and of all the Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thence reſulting: which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends that part of the <hi>etaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks,</hi> we call <hi>Categories</hi> or <hi>Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments;</hi> which we know to be very abſtract, they being only invented to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:52253:36"/>facilitate the Mentall diſtinction of many things, which we commonly ſee confus'd in Nature. Now who can doubt, but it will be more eaſy to ſhow to a Child the Riſing and Setting of the Sun, and Moon, and the other Principles of <hi>Coſmography,</hi> which they may be directed to ſee without vexing them with Abſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and afterwards to make them paſs to <hi>Geography,</hi> and the other Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences depending thereon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to the different Inflections or Accidents of Speech, who ſees not, that they depend on a thouſand eq<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions from Perſons, time paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, preſent, and to come? That the <hi>Infinitive</hi> comprehends in its <hi>Idea</hi> the abſtraction of all the differences of Time, Numbers and Perſons? And that in the Times, given to it, it is nevertheleſs <hi>Infinitiue,</hi> that is, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite, becauſe it containes in its <hi>Idea</hi> the Abſtraction from all Perſons?
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52253:36"/>That the diſtinction of thoſe <hi>Moods</hi> depends on the diſtinction, which is between the <hi>Idea</hi> of the ſimple <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,</hi> and that of <hi>Command,</hi> and <hi>Deſire &amp;c.</hi> That the <hi>Caſes</hi> of <hi>Nouns</hi> are at leaſt as abſtracted, as the <hi>Moods</hi> of <hi>Verbs,</hi> and yet more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to underſtand? And this being ſo, who can doubt, but a Child would be more capable to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Hiſtory</hi> with ſome Figures? That the <hi>Genealogies</hi> themſelves, who make one of the greateſt difficulties thereof, would not be more eaſie to him, then the reducing of a Deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to its Primitive, call'd the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtigation of the Theme; and that it would not be more ready to him, to remember, e.g. that the King is the Iſſue of <hi>Robert</hi> Count of <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> Son of St. <hi>Louys</hi> deſcended of <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi> iſſued of <hi>Childebrand</hi> ſon of <hi>Charles Martel,</hi> borne of the Marriage of <hi>Ansbert</hi> and <hi>Blitilde</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:52253:37"/>Daughter of <hi>Clotaire</hi> the Firſt; than to ſay, that ſuch a Word is the third perſon of the ſingular number of the preter-plus-perfect Tenſe of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive of the Paſſive of ſuch a Verbe.</p>
               <p>In ſhort; there is not a Child, which you may not make compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend ſooner the Demonſtration of that Theorem of <hi>Geometry</hi> (and of almoſt all others) which ſaith; <hi>If two Sides are equall to two Sides, and the Angle to the Angle, the whole is equall;</hi> than the ſimple terms of the following Rule of <hi>Syntax,</hi> which may ſerve for an Example of many other Rules; <hi>viz.</hi> If <hi>two Subſtantives meet of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Genders and different Perſons; then the Adjective or Relatif of the Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Number muſt agree with the more noble Gender; and the Verbe being alſo of the Plural, muſt accord with the more noble Perſon, or with the latter Subſtantive; or, when the Subſtantives are of things Inanimate, the Adjective
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52253:37"/>is to be put in the Neuter Gendre, or ti muſt agree with the later Subſtantive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We might therefore teach Children to Read and Pronounce well, (which is a thing very rare and neceſſary;) to Write, to caſt Accompt; Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Geometry, (foraſmuch as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to ordinary uſe;) the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Mechanicks; the Anatomy of Man; the Principles of Phyſick; Hiſtory, and the Cuſtom and Laws of their Country. And theſe are the particulars of what may be called very Vſefull and very neceſſary know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>If you add thereto thoſe many other Arts, which regard Politeneſs or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Divertiſments, as the Hiſtory of Nature, Coſmography, Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, a generall Scheme of Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, the Hiſtory of the greateſt and moſt Illuſtrious Nations, of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and former times; that which is natural and generall in <hi>Grammar,</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:52253:38"/>(to which might be referred what is particular in ever Mother-tongue,) the <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongues, the learning whereof will be rendred very eaſy by knowing the <hi>Latin;</hi> the <hi>Greeke,</hi> Natural Philoſophy, Muſick, Engins, Perſpective, Hydraulicks, the Exerciſes of the Body neceſſary to Civil Society, as Dancing (as farr as it ſerves to a handſome garb and comely behaviour,) Riding, Fencing, Swimming, and Games of wit and dexterity. If, I ſay, all theſe things be added for thoſe, that are capable thereof (which oftner happens, than is imagin'd,) or ſome of them, for thoſe, whoſe Genius is leſs ready, we ſhall find, without amuſing Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in things altogether ueleſs, wherewith ſo to fill up that ſpace of time, that there will be many more, that will find it too ſhort for ſo many things, than there will be of thoſe, that are troubled how to ſpend it.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52253:38"/>I ſpeak not of other Arts, having already ſaid more than enough of it, not only to diſabuſe thoſe, whom ſo ſlight a reaſon ſhould deterr, but to excite all thoſe, who know the importance of the Arts, I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, to embrace with Ioy all the meanes, that may be given them for it, to paſs through them; a time, out of which we cannot think to learn them but out of ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>Yet I cannot abſtaine from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king herean <hi>Overture</hi> to thoſe, that are capable of it. We might find in the <hi>Mechanicks</hi> ſome very divertiſing and very vſefull Spectacles or Sights, which un-tiring the minds of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren would fill them with certain <hi>Idea's,</hi> raiſing their Imagination, and rendring it capable to invent and produce of it ſelf. There are few <hi>Mechanical Arts,</hi> where a man of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall endowments may not find much to learn; and I believe, that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52253:39"/>all thoſe, who ſhall give themſelves the leiſure to examine ſome of them, will find, that <hi>Socrates</hi> had reaſon to ſay, that there are none but <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> and <hi>Crafts-men,</hi> that really know any thing. <hi>Gardening, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, Chymiſtry, Weaving</hi> of <hi>Stuffs</hi> and <hi>Tapiſteries, Watch-making, Refining, Melting, Engraving, Etching, Stone—cutting, Wire-drawing, Dying, Tanning, Gunpowder-making, Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter-making &amp;.</hi> will certainly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh young men with very pleaſing and uſefull divertiſements: And 'tis not eaſy to conceive, what great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge may be drawn from thence, without which one cannot well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Study of Naturall Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. Nothing were eaſier, than to ſhew the Uſes thereof in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and to diſpoſe thoſe divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their naturall order; but that this is not a place fit to treat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:52253:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> The Conſequences of that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. I. For the Choice of a Profeſſion.</head>
               <p n="1">I. IT is therefore very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious in it ſelf to have time to enter into all that knowledg: But that advantage will doubtleſs appear incomparably greater, if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conſequences thereof. For 1. by that meanes we ſhould be able to try the naturall Capacity of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and their Inclination, by ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively preſenting to them all thoſe different Principles, and all thoſe Arts; among which we might chuſe that, to which they ſhould be found to be moſt diſpoſ'd: Which is of great importance for the ſetling of men in Civill Society's.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:52253:40"/>
               <p>And the Sight thereof ought not to offend thoſe, who are reſolved not to engage their Children but in high Profeſſions. How worthy and honourable ſoever a Profeſſion be, the perſon, that is inveſted with it, may be but little worth and of ſmall eſteem, if he have no natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſpoſition to it; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, he that excells in a mediocre condition, may render himſelf very conſiderable. The Arts of <hi>Painting</hi> and <hi>Architecture</hi> are Civil and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Profeſſions, but perhaps leſs honorable than that of a <hi>Lawyer,</hi> yet there is no rational man, that would not much rather be <hi>Monſieur le Brun,</hi> or <hi>Monſieur Manſard,</hi> than a weak <hi>Advocat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would therefore be a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to youth, to be able to try themſelves, and to be try'd by wiſe men, upon the generall view, that ſhould be allow'd them of ſo many
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:52253:40"/>different Arts. But then, this would alſo be a great advantage to Arts. For 'tis beyond doubt, that, if thoſe, whoſe Vnderſtandings have been open'd by Letters and Learning, did take them in hand, whether it were to practice them, or only to take good notice of them, they would in a ſhort time improve them, and adde to them many things, which elſe nothing but Chance would introduce, and which ordinarily is not introduced, but in a long tract of years.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> II. For Manners.</head>
               <p n="2">II. THat Generall View of Arts would not only ſerve to render men Able, but alſo to make them more Honeſt and more Vertuous. It would be a means to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:52253:41"/>keep them from all Idleneſs; for it would prove a delightfull occupation, and a prevention of ſpending precious time in trifles or doing ill. And who doubts, but that men are often out of humor, for want of good or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently divertiſing employment? Which happens. becauſe they are deſtitute of knowledge, and have not been made ſenſible of many things, the underſtanding of which is very delightfull and very harmleſs. Who can doubt, that the Ignorance and inſenſibility, which is among men concerning ſuch things, is the ſourſe of ſo much trifling Converſation, and of ſo many ridiculous playes and divertiſements, which are not tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable but when men are tired of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious buſineſs, and which yet ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny make their only buſineſs, being tedious to themſelves all their life time, and yet not underſtanding, that there are other things, that may
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:52253:41"/>be delighted in? In ſhort, who can believe, that a Man, having the uſe of his ſenſes, can without a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle forbear <hi>vicious</hi> pleaſures, if his <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Eares</hi> have not been inured to find a ſenſible pleaſure in ſuch objects, as of themſelves doe not lead to vice, and if his <hi>Mind</hi> have not been diſpoſed to find plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in things abſtracted from Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (as are the <hi>Pure Mathematicks,</hi>) or in the other Sciences, that are more Materiall, but ſuch as have leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Objects of the Senſes, which commonly are the ruine of all men.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, that all thoſe things will never breed <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Vertue, nor yet <hi>Morall</hi> vertue, becauſe there lurks a ſnare in them all, and they may be turn'd to ill uſe; but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but believe, that 'tis eaſier to be morally honeſt <hi>with,</hi> than <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> them. And beſides it ſeems, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52253:42"/>
                  <hi>Morall</hi> vertue is a diſpoſition to <hi>Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> vertue; ſince that, when at length we are become, <hi>for example,</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and Iuſt, upon what motive ſoever, we need no more but to change the Object, to render that Temperance and that Iuſtice <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and that this change of Object, how impoſſible ſoever it may ſeem to the ſole ſtrength of Nature, ſeems leſs difficult, than the change of Life.</p>
               <p>But 'tis not only in that, where this Way of inſtructing Children may ſerve to form their Manners; but alſo herein, that it puts Children into a condition to returne early to be under the Conduct of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Mothers, who doe love and practice Chriſtian integrity. As there are but very few of ſuch, we muſt avow, that, how great ſoever that advantage be, it regards but few perſons.</p>
               <p>This we would not have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:52253:42"/>ſtood, as if we derogated from the Vertue of thoſe, who employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a publick way to inſtruct Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; All we would ſay, is this, that 'tis very hard, to take parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular care of Children, that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated in Common; and that, unleſs it ſhould be thought fit to alter the ordinary and received Method of Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies (which perhaps would meet with great difficulties from intereſt, incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and humerſomneſs) that cannot be done for them in Common, what may be done in private; and doe you what you can, you ſhall never give them in thoſe places the <hi>Air of the World,</hi> I mean, that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and deportment, which depends from a free and uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted manly converſe, without which it will be very hard to mould their Spirit and their Manners.</p>
               <p>But yet we will grant, to the comfort of thoſe that are not qualified not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52253:43"/>able to educate their Children in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, that they may be bred in Common after a manner, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches very much to this way, we are giveing the Model of; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the perſons, with whom you entruſt them, have good Principles of Religion, conſtancy, gentleneſs and diſcretion; that they undertake not too many; and have thoſe whom they receive, conſtantly in their Eye; receiving none that are ill natur'd, or, if they chance to doe, preſently diſmiſſing them: Beſides, that they be able, if not each in particular, at leaſt all together, to inſtill into them by converſation the Generall Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of thoſe Arts and Sciences, that are of any importance.</p>
               <p>This therefore would be one of the meanes, which Parents ſhould uſe themſelves to form their Children to honeſty and good knowledge, or to make thoſe, whom they ſhall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:52253:43"/>about them, to uſe it. This would indeed prove a <hi>Courſe of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy,</hi> diffuſed through all the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their life, and reſulting from the Entertainments and Examples, that ſhould be given them by Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and Acting before them, as we would have they ſhould ſpeak and act.</p>
               <p>This would not hinder them from going to hear Orators and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, in due time; but 'tis like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they would not need it, and that this domeſtick Courſe of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, which they ſhould make with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being aware of it, would be no leſs regular nor leſs beneficiall, nor leſs compleat, than that, which they ſhould make in a Colledge. I could diſpence with my ſelf for giving a more particular and preciſe <hi>Idea,</hi> and perhaps ſhould doe better to forbear, in the Iudgement of ſome perſons, that are not convinced, that the method, wherein Philoſophy
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:52253:44"/>is taught, ſerves <hi>little</hi> to the forming of Diſcourſe, Reaſoning and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to the knowledg of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; But if this <hi>Idea</hi> is of no uſe to ſuch perſons, it will perhaps not be uſeleſs to thoſe, who are already convinced of that truth, or are willing to be informed therein.</p>
               <p>I wiſh therefore, that the <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> of Children might be made to conſiſt in ſeaſonable Speaking and Silence; in expreſſing themſelves manly, briefly, ſignificantly, and ſutably to the motions or paſſions, which every thing is to raiſe in the Spirit of Sober men; in relating and examining the reaſons of things, and valuing them according to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe worth; and in forming, from their infancy, their Geſture and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
               <p>I would have their <hi>Logick</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in accuſtoming them, with a few Rules, with many Corrections, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:52253:44"/>with a conſtant Vſe of reaſoning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right upon the moſt frequent occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of life, to determine ſeldome, to eſteem it an honour to yield to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to Iudge equitably, to ſpeak their opinion modeſtly, to diſtinguiſh doubtfull things from certainties, and the different degrees of probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and evidence from inevidence.</p>
               <p>I would teach them no other <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks</hi> or <hi>Morals,</hi> than to exerciſe them to <hi>ſuffer</hi> others, and to <hi>endure</hi> themſelves; to doe nothing in paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or at leaſt to hide their paſſions till they ſhall have maſtered them; not to lift themſelves above any man how poor or wicked ſoever; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that all is ill done, what is not done for a good end.</p>
               <p>I would have the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> read unto them, after they have been thus prepar'd: and it might be made out to them (as 'tis not diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult) that whatſoever is taught and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:52253:45"/>preſcribed there, is conſonant to right Reaſon. I am not only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that thoſe <hi>Maximes,</hi> uſed in all their Converſe and in the whole Conduct of their Life, would ſtand them inſtead of <hi>Morals,</hi> but that all other Morals are uſeleſs, and can ſerve for nothing, but to fill the head with vaine ſpeculations.</p>
               <p>After theſe things I know not, whether I ſhould ſpeak of <hi>Naturall Philoſophy;</hi> at leaſt, this I know, that Children ſhould not be <hi>troubled</hi> but <hi>diverted</hi> therewith; and I am perſuaded, that, having been taught to eſteem nothing greater in the world than <hi>Serving God,</hi> and <hi>Doing good to Men,</hi> they need employ no other time for that knowledg, than what is requiſite to ſtudy the Hiſtory of Nature, Mathematicks, and ſuch Arts, as I have been ſpeaking of, eſpecially <hi>Mechanicks, Chymiſtry,</hi> and <hi>Anatomy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:52253:45"/>
               <p>This great Art of Life, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf calls <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefull Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi> would doe the whole buſineſs. Upon this Principle one might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with them; and it would be ſo much the more eaſie to form them by this meanes to vertue, that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been bred up in the <hi>Latin</hi> tongue untill the 7th year of their Age, they would have been ſheltered from all the idle and ſottiſh converſe of meane and ſervile people, whoſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners they are elſe ſo apt to take up: And thus they would not enter into the world, but at a time, when they had already acquired ſome habit in good; nor be diſcompoſed or put out in the converſation with reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men, as other Children are, by the ill habit they have taken at that age of being idle, or employed in nothing but trifles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:52253:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> The Concluſion of this Diſcourſe.</head>
               <p>THeſe are the Advantages, which I am perſwaded may redound, from this way of Teaching the Latin Tongue, to Learning, to Arts, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, Manners, and the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Life. I know not, whether they <hi>be</hi> ſo, as they <hi>appear</hi> to me, and whether I have related them ſuch as they are; but this I know, that nothing can be too much eſteem'd, nor too well received, that is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to contribute to things ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant to humane Society.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 17. l. 16. r. <hi>be ſo.</hi> p. 23. l. ult. r. 6, or 7. years. p. 49. l. ult. r. <hi>arts.</hi> p. 66. l: 14 r. <hi>for this reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52253:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
